John McKinley Papers
John McKinley Papers
1956-1987
McKinley, John, 1921-
2 linear ft.
Writings, correspondence, memorabilia of the adult educator, proponent of Participation Training and developer of the Indiana Plan (for adult education in the church); also includes published writings by others.
2652456
Biographical History
John McKinley (1921- ) is an American adult educator, proponent of Participation Training and developer of the Indiana Plan (for adult education in the church).
McKinley received his Bachelor's degree from Indiana State University (1947) and his M.A. (1949) and Ed.D. (1960) from Indiana University. He joined the faculty of Indiana University in 1952 and taught for more than thirty years, retiring as Professor Emeritus in 1983. His focus areas were in diagnostic theory and practice in group and organizational settings, and in small group training and development. He was also interested in adult education in the church, for which he developed the Indiana Plan to assist denominations in planning adult education.
He is the author of numerous books, book chapters, articles, and papers, including Design for Adult Education in the Church and Participation Training for Adult Education. In 1975 he received the Outstanding Adult Educator of the Year award from the Adult Education Association of the USA (now the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education, or AAACE).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John McKinley Papers consist of correspondence-subject files, memorabilia, and writings.
Correspondence-subject files contain book reviews, notes on lyceums in early America, and correspondence with two churches on McKinley's Indiana Plan. Memorabilia contains letters and tributes on the occasion of McKinley's retirement in 1983. Writings contains writings by McKinley (articles, books, a dissertation) and by others (books, one dissertation).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically. Writings are subdivided into those by McKinley, listed alphabetically by title, and those by others, listed alphabetically by author.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education, as well as numerous other resources in the general collection. Please refer to for a complete listing of manuscript collections, and to for circulating items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; McKinley, John, 1921-; Peel, Donald.; Bates, Bonnie.; Blumberg, Arthur, 1923-; Golembiewski, Robert T.; Bode, Carl, 1911-1993.; Delalić, Ešref.; Kadoya, Shinji.; Leskinnen, Heiki; Leypoldt, Martha M.; McKenzie, Leon.; Rock, Michael, 1942-; Cyclical tradition.; Adult education -- Finland.; Adult education -- Yugoslavia.; Adult education -- United States.; Church and education.; Participation training.; Research in religion and education.; Religious education of adults.; Articles.; Books.; Correspondence.; Dissertations.; Manuscripts (document genre); Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John McKinley, 2008.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Book reviews of McKinley's books, 1961; undated (Box 1)
  - Boyd correspondence on the Indiana Plan, 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Lyceums, undated; photocopies of articles, research notes, etc (Box 1)
  - McKitrick correspondence on the Indiana Plan, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Peel, Donald, circa 1981 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Retirement letters, tributes, etc, 1983 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - By McKinley
    - Creative Methods for Adult Classes, 1960 (Box 2)
    - The Cyclical Tradition, undated; notes, drafts, typescripts, microfiche; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Design for Adult Education in the Church, co-authored with Paul Bergevin, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Group Development Through Participation Training, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Guide to Program Planning, 1965; 2 copies (Box 2)
    - Participation Training for Adult Education, coauthored with Paul Bergevin, 1965 (Box 2)
    - "A participation training program in a mental hospital: an experiment in adult education", 1960; McKinley's dissertation for his Ed.D. degree, Indiana University (Box 2)
    - "Participation training in perspective: problems, issues, and futures" in Viewpoints, vol. 51, no. 4, July 1975; special issue on participation training; 2 copies (Box 2)
    - "Pedantic thoughts on the meaning and nature of continuing education" in Adult Leadership, February, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Studies in Education 1960 (Thesis Abstract Series), 1961; McKinley is on p. 283 (Box 2)
    - "Material to be developed further" (Box 1)
    - "MSS to be typed" (Box 1)
  - By others
    - Bates, Bonnie / Lifeline (Melbourne): A Case Study in the Use and Training of Volunteer Telephone Counsellors, 1978; 2 copies (1 hardcover, 1 paperback) (Box 2)
    - Blumberg, Arthur and Robert T. Golembiewski / Learning and Change in Groups, 1976; heavily annotated throughout by McKinley (Box 2)
    - Bode, Carl / The American Lyceum: Town Meeting of the Mind, 1956; heavily annotated throughout by McKinley (Box 2)
    - Bureau of Studies in Adult Education / Strategies for Teaching Effectiveness: A Collaborative Experience, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Delalic, Esref / Workers' Universities in Yugoslavia: An Adult Education Modality, 1979; inscribed by author (Box 2)
    - Grattan, C. Hartley, ed. / American Ideas About Adult Education, 1710-1951, 1959; heavily annotated throughout by McKinley (Box 2)
    - International Journal of Religious Education vol. 35, no. 9, May 1959; special issue on the Christian education of adults (Box 2)
    - Kadoya, Shinji / "The application of group discussion in Japanese society", 1977; dissertation for M.S. Ed. degree for which McKinley was thesis adviser; includes note from author (Box 2)
    - Leskinnen, Heiki / The Provincial Folk School in Finland (Indiana University Monograph Series in Adult Education, No. 3), 1968 (Box 2)
    - Leypoldt, Martha M. / 40 Ways to Teach in Groups, 1967; inscribed to McKinley (Box 2)
    - Leypoldt, Martha M. / Learning is Change: Adult Education in the Church, 1971; inscribed to McKinley (Box 2)
    - McKenzie, Leon / Decision Making in Your Parish, 1980; inscribed by author (Box 2)
    - McKenzie, Leon / The Religious Education of Adults, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Rock, Michael / Grippings: Trusted Meanings on the Human Journey, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Rock, Michael / Reflections: The Human Journey, 1985; inscribed by author (Box 2)